We're going through the most
extraordinary time in human history.
Nothing else matters. This whole
funneling of all capital into
intelligence is the biggest race that's
ever happened. The game is so big that
nobody will stop. AI in 3 years has now
exceeded [music] all of the output of
all humans on Earth.
>> So that means that it's still early to
invest in AI.
I think it's Ral Pal, [music] the
co-founder and CEO of Real Vision,
>> a financial media platform delivering
institutionalgrade market insights.
>> He's [music] a respected macro investor
and former Goldman Sachs and GLG trader.
>> You've been adding more in the nasty
recent correction. I added bit of Zcash.
I didn't buy enough. Obviously, you
never do when it goes up a lot. Privacy
in the world has value and I think
people understand that more. It's a very
easy trade. It's Bitcoin with privacy.
>> You would never sell if you don't have
to. I've obviously known this for a long
time. With all of the things we've
talked about, [music] the endless
debation of currency, plus everything
going on chain, it's hard for everybody.
But if you logically think about it, we
know where the world is going. We kind
of know where the market cap is going to
be over time. So why would you ever sell
it?
>> Bitcoin going from 126 down to 60K.
>> It's a nasty correction in a bull
market. I've been in crypto since 2013.
I've seen many corrections, non-bare
markets. And when that happens to
Bitcoin, others go down more. It happens
all the time.
>> I'm not doing another event. I'm not
buying another shitcoin. I'm not buying
another NFT.
>> It's all the same. I'm never drinking
again.
>> I'm not going to demar it again. But
that's a terrible one.
>> Yeah, thank you. I don't want to hear
that one. [laughter]
>> That was painful. Thank you.
>> Hi everyone. This is the little bit that
I know none of you like that can help us
make a huge difference for this show and
we want to take it next. 71% of the
people who regularly watch When Shift
Happens have not subscribed. And so all
I'd ask you if you want to make a huge
difference is the following. If you've
seen this show before and you like it,
help me, help my team, hit the subscribe
button and we'll continue to build this
show for you. Thank you.
I've been traveling for six weeks
non-stop
in Europe and then here and then in in
then in New York and I fly to Singapore
for 10 days and I go back to Europe.
>> Yeah, I've just done London, Geneva.
>> You go in Geneva with the Swissborg.
>> Yeah. And then Athens.
>> I was the Yeah, he went to Athens with
>> No. Yeah, I went to their thing.
>> Yeah. He's a great guy.
>> Super nice. Super nice.
>> Amazing. I mean actually I think all of
them are very nice. They have like very
good good people.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Like us.
>> Exactly like us.
>> Like everyone should be good people. Get
>> out of the way. Yeah. See that?
>> Ah we got some new friends here.
[laughter]
>> Is that a gold card?
>> I've got one.
>> You have it? Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> But what is it for? This is cast card.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Oh, nice. Beautiful.
[snorts]
>> Do you use it?
>> No. Do you?
>> But do you use the the Apple Pay thing?
For me, I just
>> I can't use I can't use Apple Pay on in
the My phone's registered in the Cayman
Islands.
>> Ah, okay. Interesting. For me, I just
spend my life on stable coins and on
cast. Just Apple Pay, Apple Pay, Apple
Pay, Apple Pay.
>> It's like a It's like an addiction. The
problem is like you don't realize it's
money, right? It's the same as when you
buy some Bitcoin or some shitcoin, you
don't realize it's actual money. Now
with stable coin you just like Apple pay
Apple pay for everything and you're like
oh [\h__\h] like this is this is this is
going this is going fast
>> buying NFTts
>> you know you don't think you're spending
money but you are [snorts and laughter]
>> well funny money in the real money world
and they're both different
>> why is that the case like what happens
in human brain that we don't realize
>> and the funny money is much bigger than
right you go you go for I mean we're in
the US you go for a steak the the other
morning I I landed in New
I was I was having steak and eggs in New
York airport GFK.
I look at I look at the the breakfast
and I'm like, "Okay, $48 steak and
eggs." I'm like, "Okay, it's not cheap,
but I want steak and eggs." I mean, it's
actually very expensive. The total bill
was 75
with uh the tax plus the tip for for a
freaking steak and egg, right? So, I'm
like, "What the [\h__\h] 75 bucks on steak
and egg breakfast. Like, this is
retarded." But then you'll spend 100
times that that or a thousand times that
on some NFT that then goes down 80% and
you'll be happy. How is that possible?
>> I don't know. It's it's the it's the
weirdest thing. It's because we we live
in two economies, right? And this
economy grows at what 50% to 150% a
year, even though we've had a few not
years of it not growing that recently.
And the other one grows at 2% a year.
>> And so of course you're going to use
money from that one. And this feels like
a whole different world.
>> Doesn't feel real.
>> No.
>> How [snorts] are we doing, Raul?
>> We're exhausted from travel. I've done
enough. I've done enough traveling
there. I think I've been at home in
Grand Cayman. I think I worked out 10
days in the last four months.
>> Wow.
What have you been doing for all this
time?
>> Well, part of it is my girlfriend lives
in Texas, so I spend time there. But
then I I don't even know this like there
was the real vision event that was in
Miami. There was a my asset management
event that was in Miami. I've been to
New York a few times. I've been to
Europe. I've been I don't know just
endlessly on a plane.
>> I don't know how many flights I've taken
this year. Less than you. But I've done
at least 50 flights.
Is it 50? Can't be there.
>> You're doing better than me actually.
[laughter]
>> You're doing much better than me. I mean
much worse than me. Like I thought I was
bad.
>> Yeah, but yours are all long haul
mainly.
>> Yeah. You're going you're doing insane
things.
>> I was supposed to have my first half of
the year kind of lined up. I was like,
I'm going to have good podcast for the
first six months. I'm just going to have
to go to token 249 in Dubai and for the
first time in two or three years. I will
have like a managed life and I can
>> when you pretended to have a girlfriend.
>> Well, actually I still have her.
>> How? It's impossible.
>> Still have her. She travels with me a
lot. [snorts]
>> But anyway,
>> that's what I do. I mean, Lindsay comes
with me all the time. It's the only way.
Yeah, but then the freaking war happened
and then Dubai token doesn't happen. I'm
like, what's the next Dubai
consensus in Miami? [\h__\h] Like, because
everyone was, we're not going to Dubai.
We're going to Miami. I'm like, another
[\h__\h] flight to to the US.
>> And I was like, I'm not doing anything
else. No more events. I'm done with it.
I'm done.
>> And then I'm at the SU event just now.
They're like, you are coming to SU base
camp. It's at token 2049.
>> Like it's in October. I'm like, I'm just
trying to go on holiday in October.
Nobody got to come. So, it's like and I
know there'll be somebody else will
force another thing in my diary.
>> I'm not doing another event. I'm not
buying another shitcoin. I'm not buying
another NFT.
>> It's all the same.
>> Yeah. We're just Yes. Yes.
>> I'm never drinking again. [laughter]
[snorts]
>> I wanted to make a bad joke, but I'm not
going to I'm not going to do it. I'm not
going to marry it again, but that's a
terrible one.
>> Yeah. Thank you. I don't want to hear
that one.
[laughter]
>> So,
>> [snorts]
>> That That was painful. Thank you.
[laughter]
>> Let's get serious here.
>> Go for it.
>> Let's look at what's happening with the
markets, the stock market. First,
there's this funny video that you
reshared and commented couple of weeks
ago.
It's this video of this kind of cartoon
character that say, "I love this market.
I really do. [snorts] It's so easy to
make money. It's actually free. You have
the US promising to buy everything
forever. Just buy the [\h__\h] dip, you
[\h__\h] idiot. And you will make money,
too. If you have no money, then borrow
money at a ridiculously low rate and buy
the [\h__\h] dip. Then tell your friends
to do the same. It's not a pyramid
scheme, you idiot. It's a buy the
[\h__\h] dip scheme. Just shut the [\h__\h]
up and buy the [\h__\h] dip, you idiot.
[snorts] What's happening with the stock
market that just goes up forever?
>> There's two things. Obviously,
liquidity, right? That's the one
fundamental we're seeing, liquidity
expansion. The other thing is we're
going through the most extraordinary
time in human history. Nothing [snorts]
else matters. This whole funneling of
all capital into intelligence is the
biggest race that's ever happened.
>> It's the race of nations. It's the race
of corporations. It's the race of
everybody. And so of course it's going
to suck every single piece of capital
because you can't slow it down.
>> Tell me what about this race?
>> There is no world in which you can allow
one superpower to have AGI.
>> Mhm.
>> So there has to be two. There's only two
nations in the world who can afford to
do it. That's the US and China. No
nation can now game theory suggests that
no nation can now stop because the other
one will get the advantage.
So there is nothing that can stop this.
Now it doesn't mean we can't have a bare
market at some point whatever but even
then you play through things like people
were fearing like there's people
borrowing money in this it's all going
to blow up. Okay, let's say let's say
Open AI blows up. They run out of money.
That's the doomous thing. What happens
the next second that's announced?
>> Is the US going to say, "Oh, we're going
to lose one of the largest AI firms."
They're going to say, "Right, what we're
going to do is we're going to auction
off the assets immediately to Microsoft,
Google, and everybody else who will buy
them in seconds." Because if they sell
it to one company, that one company
doubles their compute overnight and then
wins the entire game, which you can't
allow either. You can't allow one
company to have the advantage.
So the game is so big that nobody will
stop. All of the Iran game, all of the
Venezuela game, it's all the same game.
It's converting, which I call the
universal code, converting units of
energy into units of intelligence. Every
single process is this. So the So it's
too big to fail.
>> Yeah.
>> Therefore, might the [\h__\h] dip, you
[\h__\h] idiot.
>> That's right.
>> But forever. Like, does it ever end?
>> Well, the you know, this is a hard
question because we actually wrote about
in global macro investor a case that it
doesn't end until we get to the economic
singularity and and we don't really know
how companies work anymore and all of
that kind of stuff.
>> What What is the econ economic
singularity? Economic singularity is
when the system is no longer capable of
dealing with the speed of technology
and that's all institutions. The economy
itself, how we measure the economy, you
know that magic formula of population
growth plus productivity growth plus
debt growth. When you bring in AI and
robots as population, we've gone from a
maximum population of 9 billion people
that we are today and we can go to 18
billion, 100 billion, a trillion people.
We can make infinite agents.
Yeah, Elon's talking about the robot
will be the largest single product ever
sold.
>> Okay, there's a billion robots. Okay,
that makes a difference. But when you're
talking about
10 billion
50 billion agents, we have no
comprehension what that means. So the
economic system just doesn't function.
It's moving so fast now. So almost all
technological adoption in all of history
have been met law. So they they kind of
grow in that log channel. Look at Google
chart from its day one. Look at um
Facebook. Look at the NASDAQ. Look at
all of them. They're all the same chart.
And that's mass law. Now the issue is is
AI is the first ever recorded example of
Reed's law. So Reed's law was
theoretical. It's not observed in
biology. We don't see it in things like
viruses. Doesn't exist. Now it exists.
>> Mhm.
>> And so what we're seeing is um Reed's
law is Meetoff's law squared. So it's
the exponential of the log channel. The
exponential of the exponential. So to
put it in terms that people understand,
ARC put out a piece of research about
showing the annual output of words,
estimated annual output of words of all
of humanity each year from the Gutenberg
press in 1500 to today. AI in three
years has now exceeded per year all of
the output of all humans on Earth in
terms of words by 2028. So this is now
call it six years 5 years after AI
really came out. It will have produced
more words than all of humanity has ever
produced in sum total.
>> So the charts of all these AI things are
this anthropic revenues never been seen
before.
>> He was he was on an interview this
morning saying well we kind of [\h__\h] up
a bit because we were expecting a 10x
growth and we got an 80x growth in the
first quarter. [snorts]
>> Crazy. I mean, it's also crazy amazingly
good.
>> It's incredible. Yeah. But [laughter]
but this is what we're dealing with,
right? So the economic singularity is
when right when you've got economic
agents that can form capital, that's
what memecoins are about. We've talked
about this in the past, right? Instant
capital formation, instant capital
destruction.
>> They can build instant businesses,
digital businesses. They can they can
take a market quickly and then disappear
when the market opportunity goes.
Where's the role of these giant
lumbering corporations?
Um, you know, who who are the workers in
that economy? How does economic growth?
We can have 50% economic growth
and we somehow need to capture that and
give it back to humans as well. So the
economic singularity is that it's when
the system no longer functions
um because everything is moving so fast.
So if you [snorts] think about if we
talk about orders of magnitude how much
faster this is the biological substrate
carbon
it produces outputs of um um output
speed of 1 millisecond human thought
stuff like that neurons firing
silicon when you put and this is this is
how stupid this is this is how [\h__\h]
amazing we're putting electricity
through sand
and creating intelligence
Right? Silicon is the second most common
thing on Earth. We're now putting
electricity through it and creating
better intelligence. It's wild. And this
whole process is
now produces intelligence at six orders
of magnitude faster. So it moves at a
million times the speed of a human
neuron.
>> Quick one. I want to thank our partners
who help us make this show possible.
Thank you, Treasure, my favorite cold
wallet to store my Bitcoin and crypto
and make sure I sleep well at night. If
you want to sleep well at night, too,
you can order your treasure wallet with
my promo code WH10
and get a 10% discount. Check out my
treasure link in the description down
below. Big thanks to my good friends at
Bitwise Asset Management for backing
today's conversation. Bitwise is a
global crypto asset manager with 11
billion dollars in client assets and
more than 70 crypto solutions. That
includes ETFs, index funds, SMAs, custom
option strategies, staking, vaults, and
more. However you want to invest in
crypto, the experts at Bitwise have you
covered.
So that means that it's still early to
invest in AI because all this stuff is
going completely exponential. We see all
these stocks going complete nuts
and people in crypto a bunch have
already left. Some others are like [\h__\h]
man. Like this thing is like this thing
is like crypto in 2020 2020 2021
vertical. What am I doing here? Maybe I
should for a but I don't want to get
burnt. Like what do people do?
>> I don't know if they want to bet on AI.
>> So I can't see how it stops
because the race is so big. M. So what
is the US going to do? Is it going to
withdraw liquidity
and then everything slows down? Well,
maybe. But if China doesn't, then they
there's a real game here that has to be
played. [clears throat] And don't
forget, they've rolled all of the debt
to the short end anyway. So that's kind
of an ongoing process. You just keep
issuing debt, issuing debt. So I don't
know if they tighten liquidity unless we
end up with a larger inflation. But what
Scott Besson is saying
is we're going to run the the economy
like the Greenspan is. And what [snorts]
that means was Greenspan basically came
in,
cut rates, and then did nothing. It did
literally nothing because it the economy
was hot from 95 till 2001.
Headline inflation was going up a bit,
but he's like productivity will take
care of it because of the internet. And
so core inflation was flat. They're
going to do the same thing. They've said
it very clearly. So that's why Walsh
goes in, he does nothing. He cuts rates
and then does nothing. Just gets out of
the way. Let's productivity miracle take
the rest and then let the economy grow
faster than the debt pile so debt to GDP
goes down. That's the only game they can
play. Um
>> are you playing the AI bet or trend? Um
certainly within Global Macro Investor
and Realvision Pro, we've got a whole
load of recommendations since I came up
with the whole um exponential age thesis
which was basically this. I just didn't
imagine it was going to go this fast. So
I've had most of the those kind of names
for a while. I still think the crypto
bet is one of the superior bets in the
space. It just doesn't feel like it
right now.
>> So you think it's still superior to AI?
um
>> or more like in terms of risk adjusted
>> I think
>> returns
>> in general you'll end up over extended
period of time making more money out of
crypto than you will out of the bigger
hyperscalers and stuff like that. Sure
you know it's difficult to compete with
the chip companies. They're the single
most important part of the units of
energy into units of intelligence
process. to all capital flows there and
there seems to be no signs of this
stopping. Literally every one of them
has been on television in the last week
saying we are booked out for 3 years and
we have to book out beyond that. There
is such a scramble for chips that now X
AI is giving their older data centers to
Anthropic who can't get enough chips.
Nobody can get enough compute and nobody
can get enough energy right now. I mean
we've never seen anything like this.
There's there's been nothing like it.
And unlike the um unlike the tech boom
in the late '9s, there's no debt here
really. It's very little. So, it's being
run out of cash flow of the biggest most
cash generative firms in history as
well. I don't know how this stops.
[snorts]
This is a crypto podcast. Although we
talk about AI, marriage,
>> fake girlfriends, all of those things.
[laughter]
>> [snorts]
>> Crypto markets contrary to
stock market aren't going up forever.
>> At least not right now.
>> They are going up forever.
>> Ah.
>> What has been happening in crypto?
>> So crypto
there's only a certain amount of
liquidity in the system.
>> The US withdrew liquidity for the
government shutdown. That lags crypto by
3 months. It hit crypto that was 1010
was in the middle of all of that.
Liquidity is picking up again. Crypto's
picking up again. But there's a gap
because NASDAQ because of this massive
need for capital and investment in the
space. It just sucked in capital. The
Chinese for a period of time bought a
lot of gold in that gold rally. So what
happened was the riskiest of assets, the
furthest duration assets, which is SAS
companies and crypto produced identical
charts and they just got left behind for
a bit. But what's happened is
literally everything's changed because
in that period from that period of
October
um last year
we birthed economic agents
and they're scaling everywhere.
Everybody's building them. So what
you've got is it it dawned on me
suddenly is like everyone's like yeah
agents are going to use you know wallets
and blah blah blah. But then when you
play it through from what I've been
talking about the speed of which this is
happening this means crypto has an
infinite TAM
the total addressable market is all of
the agents and they will be economic
actors in their own right building their
own businesses stuff like that so it's
changed everything. So when you were
saying crypto is going to like hundred
trillion dollars or maybe half of that
if we miss this was based on humans.
>> Yeah.
Yeah. It it was now it's still Metcov's
law. It still follows the log trend and
that would take us still there. You
might get there a bit earlier, but what
it kind of means is it just keeps going
because a the debasement of currency
won't stop until debt to GDP collapses.
We're not there yet. GDP growth is not
fast enough. We need to get through the
economic singularity. Then
>> we see, you know, the global
coordination rails of of uh blockchain
being used for more and more things.
Don't forget the entire financial system
is going onto these rails
>> and you get to frontr run it. They've
announced what they're going to do and
I've always said this. We've been able
to frontr run the institutions all the
way through and people get exasperated
with crypto because it went down for a
year and you're like look at the [\h__\h]
picture. You've got an infinite TAM the
entire financial system going on these
rails. The Clarity Act being passed the
government will not stop debasing the
currency.
>> Mhm.
So it just keeps going.
>> So the worst is over for crypto.
>> Yeah.
>> Why?
>> Because the liquidity is flowing.
Liquidity is flowing in the US.
Liquidity is flowing in in in
uh China. It's flowing um across the
world. So liquidity is going up. Global
liquidity keeps going. It's
accelerating. US liquidity is
accelerating. So therefore, nothing to
worry about yet.
So for you, Bitcoin going from 126 down
to 60K is is not a bare market.
>> No,
>> it's a nasty correction.
>> It's a it's a nasty correction in a bull
market. Now, I've been in crypto since
2013. I've seen many corrections,
non-bare markets of 50% in Bitcoin. But
people forget this every time. And when
that happens to Bitcoin, others go down
more. We've talked about this in the
past. There's a risk curve. It's
natural. Happens all the time. I think
it was Salana last cycle did down 80 in
uh in 2021 before it before it had that
massive run and that was in a bull
market year with liquidity flowing.
Happens all the time. Happened to
Ethereum happen. So it happens all the
time.
>> The difference is in 2021
when Bitcoin went down 50%.
>> Yeah.
>> It was pretty quick. Went down and then
it went back up also very quickly and
then it [clears throat] went down. It
was a bare market. This time around it's
kind of choppy and it takes time and
months and
>> so
>> that's probably why people are
>> Yeah. And what might you get from the
other side of it?
>> You might get a longer more larger bull
market, right? Cuz don't forget the the
Bitcoin pull back in 2021 as you said
was
>> it was
what something like January to July
>> and it was back alltime highs in
November. So it's actually six months of
falling. So, when did Bitcoin make its
all-time high? December last year,
>> I think.
>> So, it's only, you know, it only went
down the equivalent number of months.
Didn't go down that long. Um, but let's
see. The longer it takes to go up, the
more extended it becomes, I think.
Some people talk about I mean there's
this K-shap recovery that's been talked
about for a long time in um the economy
and uh and in the stock market but now
some people talk about Kshape um
recovering crypto most assets won't come
back
and worse some companies that are doing
well cannot be invested into for example
stable coin companies it's extremely
hard there's no token you have to do
some private equity or VC see stuff to
be able to buy them.
That's why people are pissed basically
because
they haven't really made money and they
feel like this there's a bunch of people
or quite a lot who say actually all
these crypto coins are dead but there is
stable coins RWA
bitcoin and like a few other things that
will go up but people can't buy these
companies. Therefore, they feel like the
the the the promise of I can invest
early in something that will go up,
which they also couldn't do in AI,
right? The the kind of promise is
broken.
>> What What do you think about that?
>> I think it's not true.
>> I think product market fit wins
hyperlquid.
>> You know, you've seen it. Product market
fit wins. So, there are plenty of
opportunities. just because your
[\h__\h] token doesn't go up, [laughter]
you know, it the market owes you
nothing,
you would just have to be better at
doing a job.
>> That's a good one, actually. The market
owes you nothing. But people have been
That's why a lot of people left pistol
also over the last two years because
people have been um used to easy money
by closing their eyes, everything going
up.
>> We haven't had the full [snorts]
accelerated the banana zone phase. We've
not had that because liquidity was still
subdued in 2024. So we had good year
2022 from the low. So end of the year,
2023 was a great year and then 24 peted
out and that was it. Um Bitcoin
continued for a bit, but really we just
haven't had the acceleration period. So
people have the cycle has extended and
everyone's given up on year four of
potentially fiveyear cycle, maybe longer
now. I don't know. I don't know how
broken the cycle is by what's going on.
It's like, you know, don't forget the
K-shaped economy. So, tech economy is
booming. The uh the real economy is not.
>> So, what are they trying to do? They're
trying to cut rates to help
regular people. The ISM that we've
talked about in the past is now ripping
positive as crypto rises. Same thing.
And they're going to have the largest
infrastructure investment in the history
of the world is about to happen. in data
centers and all of that buildout and
that's going to employ a lot of people
in construction services everything and
we're going to have a boom and that
money gets saved spent or invested and
people will come to the casino as they
always do uh in the crypto market. So
again, I don't have an issue. I also
think that people misunderstand
the rise of stable coins, RWAs, the
finance
system bringing stuff on chain. They're
like, how do we participate in this?
Just own the [\h__\h] token. This this
like
>> the underlying layer one
>> layer one. I the layer one trade is so
simple.
>> It's so obvious. It's the big trade. It
is the I talked about this the universal
basic equity layer for all of us. If we
are going to see the largest
um parts of the economy given over to AI
and agents
and they're going to use crypto rails.
>> Mhm.
>> We just get to own the layer ones and we
participate in their success.
Right. We didn't get that with the
internet and nobody there's no excuse
for people not to do this.
You've been adding more as you always do
in the nasty recent correction.
>> What did you add?
>> Um, I added some Zcash.
>> Why?
>> I bought more Suie obviously. Um, but I
added bit of Zcash.
Last time you said
because it was going crazy in December,
you said I'm going to wait for for it to
go down and I'm going to see how it uh
how it plays out and how it reacts.
>> Correct. That's what exactly what I did
>> and into the correction um I started
buying some.
>> Um I didn't buy enough obviously you
never do when it goes up a lot. Um but
because Zcash is so we we've talked a
lot about smart contract layer ones
right in the world of you know store of
value there is only one well there was
only one really
>> but now we've got another one which is
it has a subsection of that and I think
you know I was talking to Barry Silva
about this the other day is to assume
that it could be 10% of Bitcoin 5% great
in terms of you know how much economic
value it has privacy in the world has
value for people
>> and I think people will understand that
more and so therefore it's a very easy
trade it's Bitcoin with privacy.
>> Yeah.
>> You know I love a left curve trade and a
right curve trade.
>> Yeah.
>> The midcurve is well they're going to
ban it. They're going to do [\h__\h] I've
lived this all through all of my crypto
career. Right. It's always been they're
going to ban it. They won't allow you.
They won't do it.
>> What's your left curve trade? The left
curve trade is it's Bitcoin with
privacy.
>> What's the right curve trade?
>> The right curve trade is also quantum
proof.
>> And what you're actually doing is
proofing yourself somewhat to the power
of government that uses has AI control
over the people. All of this thing, you
know, the bad outcomes, it gives you a
lot of different
um attributes that are probably very
valuable.
And people don't know it now, but in the
future, what's the probability? It's
reasonably high.
>> Quick shout outs to our legendary
long-term windshift events partners,
without whom none of this would be
possible. Thank you to Cast, my go-to
global money app to store, earn, move,
and spend stable coins across 170 plus
countries directly with Apple Pay or a
physical card. On top of that, I can
also get paid in USD and euro with my
cast virtual account. Use my promo code
shift S sh H I FT and my link below to
get 10% off your membership. Earn up to
3% instant USD cash back on every card
spend and get up to $250 in cash for
referring your friends. No banks, no
borders, just money that moves with you
with stable cash rewards. Big thanks to
our sponsor Sumub, the leading full
cycle verification platform for crypto,
trusted by eight out of 10 of the
world's largest exchanges. If you're
building in crypto, you already know
fraud moves fast and regulators never
chill. Sumup gives you full cycle
verification in one stack. KYC, KYB,
transaction monitoring, and even full
travel rule compliance across 1,800 plus
virtual asset service providers. Their
AI flags suspicious behavior and account
takeovers in real time before damage is
done. Check the link in the description
to learn more.
When you add an asset like Zcash, how do
you think about allocation
portfolio wise? You have like a target.
I want to put like 5% 10%.
>> You just say I have a dollar amount.
>> Unfortunately, it's just been trading
too strong. So, it's
>> Yeah, it's been crazy.
>> Yeah. So, I didn't I just I was going to
buy some and then I bought some and then
I was going to buy some more and then I
forgot because I was traveling and then
it's like, oh [\h__\h] it's up 50%. And
then I'm like, I'm not going to do this
even though I know they're probably good
prices, but you know, you know what it's
like. I didn't execute it well. Um,
so yeah, we'll see. I won't I won't
switch around my existing portfolio for
it, I don't think. Um,
>> so this has new cash.
>> New cash.
>> Um, but we'll see.
>> [snorts]
>> you mentioned hype before
and I talked to Dante and he mentioned
hype multiple times without me even
asking about it. So I was like, "Oh, the
macro guys talk about hype and hyperlid
which I think everyone kind of like
started to realize during the war and
the weekends. Oh, this this thing is
actually helping to price oil markets
during the weekends when there is war."
and you're a macro investor, so you must
have thought like, wow, this is like
something really new and kind of
crossing the chasm into like mainstream
and traditional finance, which is what
we're really trying to do in crypto.
What are your thoughts on
hyperlquid and what these guys are
doing? Even on the hype token, are you
like not tempted to to do something
about that?
>> If I don't use it,
>> I wouldn't buy it and I'm just not a
trader. So, you know, we talked about
that. So, it's just not for I don't use
PES, I don't use leverage, I don't use
any of this stuff. So, I get it, but it
is a niche within a broader ecosystem
and it's a great one. You can have great
niche products.
>> Um, but it has no real motor around it.
I mean, Robin Hood are going to come
after that as fast as they can and
eventually Coinbase, too. Now, can Hyper
out execute them? Possibly. Probably. I
don't know. Don't really have a view on
it. Um, but it's not my trade. Now,
24-hour markets,
great, but I mean, literally everybody's
talking about that.
>> There's a saying in finance and
investing, and I think in life in
general, in hindsight, it was obvious.
>> Yes.
>> This of said, it's often said by people
who have regrets, who missed a trend,
didn't invest.
We're lucky to have you here, Raul, the
man who can read long-term trends. and
you're saying that there are a couple
things that are actually obvious in
foresight.
Let's go through them one by one so
people don't have an excuse in 10 years
to say in hindsight it was obvious.
The first one you mentioned before smart
contract layer one will acrewue a larger
percentage of crypto total value over
time as the investable infrastructure
layer.
>> Yeah.
>> Can you explain? So this is the univers
basic equity idea right we've
[clears throat] for the first time we've
got a globalized infrastructure digital
infrastructure unlike the internet that
we can participate in that the AI and
others will use and we get to reap the
benefits of them right this is this is
the trade-off we're giving to them
taking part of our knowledge work away
is they're going to give us the ability
to make money from their economy that
they create
over time the layer ones People don't
understand this is the lay ones. If you
think of all big
networks that are important for
infrastructure, whether it's operating
systems, uh whether it's cloud, all of
that, there's basically
three to four main players.
Then there's a a bunch of specialists
and then there's a tale of stuff, but it
really accumulates to three or four to
five people.
>> This will be the same. So it's going to
be around three, four, five chains as
layer ones. Then there'll be specialists
like hype is a specialist. You know, can
that continue? It's a one vertical niche
thing. Okay, great. Um, there'll be
somebody who does something slightly
different, privacy, but that's really on
the Bitcoin side of the ledger, which is
a non-smark contract.
>> Um,
so the infrastructure layer becomes much
more important than people understand.
We've talked about in the past, every
ticket becomes an NFT. you know every
all of these things the whole finance
system comes on board that's all
acrewing value to layer ones how I try
and explain the value of a layer one
is Ethereum
okay so if you were to pull the plug on
Ethereum today how much economic value
do you destroy
>> I mean huge every layer two
all of DeFi all of the real world assets
all of NFTTS
everything that's been built on ETH goes
to zero. ETH is probably undervalued for
that already. Let alone the growth rate
of these things and let alone thinking
well the finance system is going to come
a lot on ETH and layer 2s and stuff like
that. So that's how you got to think
about what is the value of that
infrastructure.
Uh and so if you think of Bitcoin,
Bitcoin has one job and it has one
target which is global savings.
And so Bitcoin is a power law
distribution because over time you can
only get to 100% of global savings.
Infrastructure layer can scale
infinitely which is why again Google and
all of those companies have just been
like that on a log regression channel.
>> So that means for you that the layer one
whichever you choose
ei
should be a majority of your portfolio.
And I I still think you [clears throat]
know I've done a lot of work. just
presented this Siri live about this is
for me and I know I'm biased because I'm
on the board but but this is from deep
analysis is it is clearly ETH has the
largest amount of economic and
intelligence density of any of these
Salana has is proven and then we're
talking about remember three or four
>> who else the only one through the
analysis that I got to was
>> because it has more TVL per user than
Salana does and it's a lot younger. No.
And when the market fell 80% it didn't
lose any economic density in fact
maintained it. There was only three
tokens that maintained economic density.
ETH Salana Sui
and when you look at SU on a bunch of
other basis you've got the output of
intelligence because it's
programmability the speed and all of
this stuff. So I just think there's a
basket of four or five you can own layer
ones and you can go to the beach and in
10 years time you can fly back from the
beach in a private jet.
[snorts]
>> I thought we don't like to travel
anymore. [laughter]
>> It's a private jet.
>> Private jet. Yeah. It's
>> it's different. It's different. I don't
know. I've never flown in a private jet.
So
>> not yet. Not yet. [snorts]
In 10 years,
>> in 10 years,
>> layer ones that can output the largest
amount of intelligence per unit of
energy will outperform over time.
>> Yes.
So, this is this I've not really fully
released the entire thing on the
universal code. I've written about it.
People don't really understand it yet,
but the there's [clears throat] a set of
operating principles that are observable
and provable and understandable of how
the universe works. The key one is the
entire universe from atomic structure to
solar system structure
completes um continues to convert units
of energy which is the fixed all of
physics says is you can't destroy your
career energy and out of it comes
intelligence. We're part of that
process. Um, and
AI is part of that process and
blockchains are the same process.
Everything is they all are networks as
well. Every single one of them are
created by networks. And so what you've
got is an intelligent network of compute
and storage, which is blockchain. And
money, as we talked about, why does
Nvidia get more money than anybody else?
Because they're creating more
intelligence output than any other
company on Earth right now. Why is
Anthropic doing it? Because they're
produc they're producing more
intelligence output. It happens
literally everywhere. Why is the NASDAQ
outperformed? Once I discovered this
universal code, I see it everywhere in
everything. It's the organizing
principle of the universe. And what you
find is all geopolitics is based on it.
All of what human activity is based on
it. Everything is based on it. So that's
what this is about is anything with more
intelligence does well. How can you
measure that for a layer one to know
which one you should bet on or which
ones you should bet on?
>> So intelligence comes in many forms.
Firstly, intelligence of human capital.
How many builders, programmers,
developers?
Then what is the programmability and
efficiency of that programmability? How
fast does that blockchain convert energy
into
programmable outcomes? So ETH in this
case is actually not great but ETH wins
massively from the number of developers
and economic density the Lindy effects
the security all of that right so it's
it's very solid as I've said it's like
the Microsoft you know you don't get
fired for
>> ETH
>> you got Salana which is much more
efficient much faster much cheaper um
easier to deal with than ETH uh less
developers but good good density
Um you've got SU which is much earlier
but as we said it's uh it's things like
programmable um block times block
transactions of a thousand transactions
within one block. It's like a different
order of magnitude than anything else.
It's speed to finality is a different
order of magnitude. Its programmability
is a different order of magnitude. So
what you've got is provable
intelligence. now doesn't mean anything
unless you can prove that hey how many
applications does it have built on it
how many applications per user you know
that kind of stuff you start to see
these metrics and you can see density
forming it's still not there it's still
early you know you want to see you want
to see a large portion of stable coins
versus TVL which is like that is stored
energy in the system ready to be
deployed into the system right now su is
like um Swiss TVL is equivalent to the
stable coin size. You want to see twice
that or more. When you get to ETH, you
see huge amounts. So there's a there's a
bunch of indicators, but what you're
looking for is what can you do with the
chain? How little cost? So when people
look at blockchains, they look at
discounted cash flow analysis to value
them. How many how much fees does it
generate? Doesn't generate fees. ETH's
so expensive. It's [\h__\h] nonsense
because
>> because because the very purpose of a
network like this is to be the cheapest
fastest.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> So if you use discounted cash flows, you
miss the actual signal which is
cheapest, fastest, most pro programmable
will outperform over time.
the bigger user the biggest user of defy
and crypto payments will be AI agents
and their scale their scale is infinite.
[snorts]
Yeah, there's So, we've talked about
Yeah. crypto payments, right?
>> But I'm just setting up some agents now
and a lot of the time you'll start to
hit walls for API calls and all of this
stuff and there'll be a payment and it'd
be 10 cents, whatever the number is,
right? You've got tons of these micro
payments to make and then larger
economic transactions because they can
do other stuff. Fine, we kind of all
understand that bit. The DeFi bit is
really interesting.
Defi is actually much better suited for
machines than us. You don't even need a
front end. I was speaking to one of the
guys um at an event last night. I'm
like, why even bother with even a
website or a front end or anything? Just
attach, you know, allow the agents to
come do their job, leave in the fastest
possible, least friction because that's
what wins the this game.
>> Yeah.
>> And so what will agents do? Well, we're
talking about a multi-chain world.
>> [clears throat]
>> They're going to end up with even stable
coins on three different currencies or
four different currencies and they're
going to want to rebalance if they want
to put it into let's say they've got
different transactions, they got
different currencies, they will have
treasuries, of course they will. And how
will they swap? DeFi and they'll do it
instantaneously without any human
involved and we won't even see it. We
won't even see the transaction. And so
they're going to be the largest users,
sir.
>> How can someone bet on that?
buy the layer one. [laughter] It's not
that complicated. Now, I know layer ones
may not be the raciest bet. You won't
may not make the most money. And fine,
you can go to the casino if you think
you're a good VC investor and find which
are the protocols that are undervalued
versus, you know, are they getting
adoption effects. All of that that still
applies. You can still do that work.
>> Um, it's just hard. I can't do it.
>> And even the good ones can get hacked as
we've seen.
>> Yeah. or have like indirect
>> that's still hot. That's going to be
difficult. It's very difficult for them
to destroy a layer one. It's very easy
to draw an applications layer.
>> So for you DeFi is not dead cuz we've
hear now I had like some people who are
actually pretty big telling me man this
DeFi thing is dead after what happened
in the last two months. Yeah.
>> All these mega hacks.
>> Yeah.
H how how can a bank come and say or a
financial infrastructure come and say
I'm going to use my client's money on
this DeFi stuff that can get hacked $300
million.
>> So doesn't it just force people to build
better products?
I mean that's the answer, right? We're
not building good enough products.
>> Now don't forget, why have we all got
Norton antivirus or whatever on our
bloody computers? Because they get
hacked.
>> This is not just this. It's everywhere.
Every single bank has a group internally
that has to deal with hacks. They have a
reporting number of X percentage is
stolen from the bank, but they don't
make a big deal of it because they don't
want to disturb people, but it happens
at every level in everything we do.
>> You said before all financial rails will
move to blockchain rails.
>> So this was a prediction I went back uh
certain GMI I made in 2014.
I said that's before smart contracts. I
said this is the infrastructure rail for
the entire financial industry
blockchain. Um and I've been saying that
ever since. And I said you can frontr
run the institutions and now they're all
announcing it. Why? Because it's more
efficient way of output of energy
>> and you can still frontr run them
>> and you can still front run them. But
it's the most single efficient way for
the financial system to operate. The
financial system will always move to the
most efficient rails. Why? Because you
make more money. Always works that way.
>> Digital art, your favorite one, will
acrewue will acrew value vast value over
time due to wealth effect of the above.
>> Yeah. You and I have talked about this
on the podcast in the past, right? If
I'm right,
and I can't say I'm not going to be, and
we go to hundred trillion dollars over
time,
that's a [\h__\h] ton amount of money. M
>> and that is humans participating in what
is going on, right? We're participating
in the machine economy. Fantastic. The
crypto rails, the finance system, you
know, they're taking our money away from
us by coming into this. They're they're
taking our rails. No, they're they're
going to rent our rails off us and we're
going to own the tokens. So, we're going
to make the money out of all this and at
the end of it all, we'll have made a
decent amount of money and people will
buy trophy assets. And we're going
through the most ridiculous point in all
of humanity. We're going through the
point where we are not apex
intelligence.
And art records all of the stories of
our time, the culture of our time. This
is the single biggest moment in all of
humanity is in is happening as we speak.
I mean, what a time to be alive. And
tell me that art is not going to be
important. That's [\h__\h] ridiculous.
>> What's the time frame for that? because
I bought a bunch of uh Crypto Punks and
um
XCOPY.
>> Yeah,
>> I don't look at this anymore. I'm like,
you know, the thing that you don't want
to look at because it's like going up a
bit and it goes down. Oh man, this thing
is not moving.
>> Yeah.
>> The time frame is much longer.
>> Yeah. But don't forget, it's a function
of the vibrancy of the crypto economy.
>> So, you have to wait until crypto is
worth 10, 20, 30, 40, 50 trillion to
actually see a massive difference. Well,
you'll see it
>> because people will
>> the moment let's say ETH goes from
wherever it is today two and a half or
whatever
>> to [snorts]
five.
>> Is this ever happening again? [laughter]
[sighs and gasps]
>> I was talking with Dantier.
>> We are allowed to have nice things. I
know nobody believes it thinks we've
been robbed of the whole thing.
>> Five years of pain, right? So I was
talking with Dantier and was saying like
this is kind of like for for a lot of
people when NASDAQ is up 2x Bitcoin
barely has moved in five years.
Obviously it depends on what time frame
you take but if you look okay back five
years
>> it's it feels like a lost decade for a
lot of people in crypto.
>> When you ask Dan that and me that we'll
say well imagine what happens when it
breaks out.
>> That is accumulated energy that happens
>> because we know what's happening. It's
[\h__\h] obvious that they're going to be
doing all of these things. The
governments will continue to do base
currency.
>> Yeah.
>> The um financial industry will build on
these rails. The agents are coming. It's
[\h__\h] obvious. So therefore, when it
does break out, the accumulated energy
that it has is going to be something
dramatic. And people have forgotten what
the energy looks like when it hits those
markets. They've forgotten how vertical
>> it's been a long time. because people
are looking at, you know, Micron or
Intel or whatever and they're like, "Oh
my god, look at Intel stock 10-year
consolidation
explosion. I mean, literal expo
explosion." Um, I kind of think that's
where it's going now. Is that this year,
next year? Doesn't really matter. Um,
but even when ETH gets back up to the
highs of the range, let's say, you'll
see a lot more activity in NFTs
>> because people are feeling more
confident. But if it breaks through,
then everything changes.
How the hell do you structure an NFT
portfolio?
>> Um,
so I'm actually going to launch a fund
on this. Um, because so many people came
to me and said, "Well, I don't know how
to do it." And I know how to do it. I've
got the, you know, I know the best
people in the world are doing this. So,
I think we're going to launch a fund.
Um, XPAM will be able to hopefully
announce a partner that'll be doing it
with, which will be super interesting.
Uh, we're just kind of finalizing that
now. M
>> but otherwise
you know it's not easy
for somebody who doesn't know how to do
it having talked people through it. Um
>> how would you structure an NFD fund?
>> That's because I know the space very
well and the people who are going to be
involved in this know the um the space
extremely well.
>> So the fund will be structured for grail
assets. So these are the really
expensive super scarce ones that already
have proven social consensus
>> for example.
>> So
>> what's a real asset? one a one of one X
copy alien Crypto Punk a uh Sam Sprat
one of one a um people one of one you
know these things proven value trade any
anywhere between
$600,000 and
10 10 million 20 million $30 million
then the next tier down is the
interesting tier there's good convexity
which is the artists that have social
consensus
have long-term proven value,
particularly in this sideways market in
ETH for a long time that capture
attention.
There's a whole group of those who can
get wildly rerated and so they may trade
at let's say
>> for example
>> maybe one to example
>> die with the most likes who's a very uh
fantastic artist that is humorous kind
of gross but what he's doing is
commenting on the decline of middle
America. It's like a really important
commentary but also with a love affair
from middle America because he's from
Indiana. He lives in it, sees it. uh and
it's amazing work
likely because of the importance of what
he's what he's cataloging is going to
matter and so um and he's very unique in
how he does it. He's kind of like the
Huntress Thompson of artists. So I think
that's important. There's another German
artist called Kim Asendorf who's at the
cutting edge of AI and art where he's
got these incredible 3D art, but it's
made of a number of pixels, but you can
define the number of pixels because each
pixel itself is a token.
>> So, every pixel has value. And he's got
these incredible things. And these
things, these kind of um collections are
somewhere between,
you know, the really high quality ones
of those are somewhere between 20 and 40
ETH.
>> Call it call it 10 to 50 E. That that
bucket of people. Some of those can get
wildly rerated. Now, don't forget ETH
can get rerated, too. The convexity in a
trade like this, and we've talked about
this in the past, is absurd. If an
artist gets rerated from 20 to 200 ETH
and there's plenty of things that trade
at 200 E that's a 5x in that
in that and let's say over the next 10
years where's ETH 10 years I have no
idea but let's say it's 20,000
well that's a massive 100x return
because you get 10x on the NFT and ETH
terms and 10x on ETH
Because as we talked about in the
beginning, the ETH economy is not the
same as the dollar economy. If [snorts]
you're rich in that economy,
>> you'll spend more in that economy.
>> What kind of investor might be
interested in investing in into an NFT
fund?
>> So, we've spoken to a lot of people.
There's a lot of family offices,
general high net worth people who are
curious who've been in crypto, but
non-crypto uh people who are interested
in the art world.
What the other group is there's a lot of
crypto
uh OGs who've made a lot of money out of
the space and have never bought digital
art.
Uh and they're like yeah and I think it
was a big move when Mickey Mala bought
Crypto Punk's IP. It's made it public.
people is still, you know, very well
seen within the space and people
starting to get it that you can't be in
this space and not have the great one of
the best product market fits it's ever
created, which is digital art on chain.
And so I speak to a lot of them. So I
think a lot of the crypto OGs will buy
art because all of the tech tycoons
bought art, all of the real estate
tycoons bought art, all of the hedge
funders bought art. As soon as people
make a lot of money, they buy art.
Quick shout out to the legendary team at
Jupiter, the DeFi super app. Anything
you want to do on chain, from trading to
earning yield, you can just use Jupiter.
Personally, I'd recommend getting the
Jupyter wallet on either your phone or
your laptop. 10 times faster and 10
times cheaper than the competition.
You're going to love it. Thank you to
the awesome team at Athena for backing
today's conversation. Athena is one of
the fastest growing projects in DeFi
with over $7 billion in stable coin
supply and an average 11% APY on SUSD
and importantly zero DPEG since launch
which is exactly what you want from a
stable coin. Go check them out by
following the link in the description
down below.
You mentioned Grails one right before.
Does that mean that I was talking to
Jeff Park?
Um
>> Oh, it is. Sorry, before we go to that,
I missed a couple of parts of the fund.
>> Yeah, because but that's why I'm
>> Okay.
>> It's actually linked to that probably
>> I was talking to Jeff Park and he we're
talking about uh uh he was bit Bitwise
adviser and then he worked with Pomp and
and kind of Bitcoin analyst and we're
talking about real estate.
>> Yeah.
>> We're talking about real estate in in in
New York. Yeah.
>> And the ones that actually are really
worth
>> are very valuable
>> are the ones that are $20 million
penthouse, right? That those are the
one, but the $1 million flat
>> actually doesn't really
>> get value over time.
>> No.
>> So similarly, right, talking about NFTs,
you talk about the grail.
>> Yeah.
>> The the the $5 million punk, alien punk.
Well, I have a bunch of punk. Maybe two
or three, I don't know.
>> They're not grails.
Is this my $1 million flat in New York
City?
Like, should people only focus on like
the top grail NFT or what's the
>> No. A, all of this will get rerated.
It's still so small. So, the whole space
is going to get rerated.
>> Secondly, what you've got is a small
apartment in a great block,
>> right? Because in that block is the
alien punks and the cowboy punks that
have sold for 20 million, $30 million,
$20 million, $10 million. So you're
living next to the billionaire,
billionaire adjacent in the right
neighborhood. Okay, that's a pretty good
deal.
>> You know,
>> I feel better now.
>> Yeah,
>> Thank you for making me feel better.
when you're if you're if you're
searching, if you're trying to make
money and not just buying art for art's
sake, which is I highly encourage
everybody to do, but if you're actually
trying to build a portfolio of this,
then the issue is is somewhere in the
middle tier, there's artists that never
get rerated. It's like bands only get so
much popularity. Doesn't mean they're
not great bands, but that for some
reason it just doesn't become bigger.
That's the risk is is that the right
neighborhood? Is it do the right people
want to live there? It's the same thing.
>> But this would be more for artists or
could be the same. Maybe the the board
apes don't get rerated.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> Maybe the punks.
>> That's right.
>> Some punks don't get rerated for some
reason.
>> Some punks they will all get. Um, but
which ones outperform, I don't know.
>> Um, but maybe apes is a good example.
Maybe I'll never make my money back on
my Ape that I bought at the all-time
highs. Yeah.
>> Um, okay. Fine. So, maybe that's not how
it works.
>> Yeah.
>> The other part of what we're doing in
the fund, which is interesting, is we're
also going to be lending
>> against NFTTS because you
>> interesting.
>> You can do lending markets on Gandhi and
a few other places
>> and you get great yields like 15% plus
>> against assets that the fund would buy
if the lender defaulted. So, you get
them at a good price. And then with a
yield, we will obviously cover some of
the funds cost, but also reinvest in
more emerging artists. So, you're trying
to support the entire ecosystem and add
liquidity because there's tons of people
who are sitting on, you know, an alien
punk. Well, there's not tons because
there aren't many of them, but an alien
punk and they want to borrow, you know,
a million bucks because they want to buy
a house.
Well, that releases liquidity or they
want to buy some more art. Just releases
the quizzy, let it slush around. So we
we're doing all that and then we'll form
some sort of club around this as well to
get to introduce the investors to the
artists themselves so they can start
their art journey themselves by buying
art directly.
[snorts]
We talked about AI before.
Is Bitcoin a proxy for AI
as a trade?
>> Yes and no.
I mean
because Bitcoin is going after global
savings but a global savings should go
up if AI changes economic growth. So
therefore that increases the eventual
outcomes for Bitcoin itself.
Um, I think that there will be enormous
amounts of liquidity from the private
sector coming from debt that's going to
feed this cycle and that liquidity is
debasement of currency over time. So
that's good for Bitcoin.
>> Mhm.
>> And Bitcoin is a digital store of value
and we're creating an increasingly
digital world with digital intelligence.
So
>> yeah, it's fine.
>> I [snorts] think the lay one smart
contracts are a better bet on all of
this.
They just don't feel like it yet to
people
and the people the market can only have
so much focus at once and we've seen
this before in crypto bull runs. It
focus on three things and it can't see
the rest and everything pauses for a bit
and then it rotates to the next one
because the market only has so much
attention, so much capital at any one
time.
You said everyone is so focused on the
crypto cycles
when the big picture is so [\h__\h]
obvious. You would never sell if you
don't have to. Yeah, I str that that was
a I mean I've obviously known this for a
long time, but I'm just realizing now
with the agents and the fun with all of
the things we've talked about, the
endless debation of currency plus the
agents plus um everything going on
chain.
It's like why would you sell this? This
is a massive shift in mindset that I
realized I think
gets much easier when you start to
generate quite a lot of a lot of income,
right?
>> Yeah.
Because otherwise you you might have a
job which is the maj m majority of the
people and you make money but your
dreams and hope are in crypto and you
but you're like I want to trade this
thing because maybe my income every
month is good but is not enabling me to
to have an exceptional life right and I
will need so much time but when you
start to make more income
this becomes so much easier.
>> Yeah. Yeah, it it is. And I know people,
you know, it's hard for everybody. It's
hard. Um, but really, if you if you
logically think about it,
we know where the world is going.
We kind of know where the market cap is
going to be over time because it's
following Metcost law and that you could
just draw the log regression channel.
So, what why would you ever sell it?
>> Yeah. Never sell and buy every month. I
mean at some point you get back to like
the very basics after so many years
which is just just just never sell and
just buy every month.
>> So it's the left curve and right curve
is here [clears throat] right
>> and as I said I mean this is humanity's
pension plan.
>> This is what this is now because we get
to invest in the infrastructure rails of
which all the agentic economy will run.
>> We get to do that. It's a pension plan.
It'll bail you out of everything that's
happening. You just have to do it. Which
is why, you know, I first said the
economic singularity is coming and
you've got at the time six years
>> and now it's what four years away.
You've got four years to just own as
much of this [\h__\h] as possible before you
go into the biggest moments of
uncertainty. But I think blockchain
survive through the other side.
Corporations have no idea what's going
to happen over time.
>> But blockchains, oh yeah.
Can you prove with actual numbers
what we just said that buying and
holding and ideally accumulating every
month or when crypto market go down
massively outperforms trying to trade
cycles? So I I have done the work
because I've built an I' been building
an indicator for real vision to help
people with this.
>> And what I basically said is if it's two
standard deviations oversold on that log
regression channel between one and two,
you buy
um it compounds at a stupid rate. Now if
you
if you sell, how much do you sell at the
top of the cycle? Here's the problem. or
how much you reinvest back in the
bottom.
That's the hard part. If you let's say
you get
one two opportunities to to add every
four years, maybe one in the middle
cycle, one at the end of the cycle.
You got two opportunities. You just save
up money between each one of those. Do
nothing, do nothing, do nothing. You get
that like we've just had. You buy. You
go away. You keep saving money. You do
that again. Okay? That's doable for most
people.
Just keep adding to your bet as much as
you can. That obviously outperforms
everything because you never sell. If
you sell at two standard deviations, how
much do you sell? Or one standard
deviation overbought. Two gives you the
least signals, but it's a better quality
signal.
And this is where the problem is. If you
take 25% off, yes, you've got lifestyle
chips, but then you've got less money in
the casino.
If you take 50% off and you say, "Well,
I'm going to add that back at the
bottom." Good luck doing that.
>> Good luck.
>> Because people can't do it. We're seeing
it now.
>> Yeah. It's too difficult.
>> People can't do it. They're doing it now
and they're chasing all the way up. And
you you would tend to [\h__\h] it up. So on
paper, you could be an absolute amazing
compound performer if you could buy the
bottoms and sell the tops. I've been in
the industry for 35 years and I don't
know anybody who can do it.
>> [snorts]
>> I saw you recently on this traders
podcast and I I mean I have a bunch of
friends who are traders and we all know
all this stuff but like it was kind of
funny because you're saying that on a
trader podcast when this guy is
literally selling trading to all his
audience and the truth is the truth
right.
>> Well look there are look at how many
traders there are and look at how many
of them actually made a lot of money
consistently over time from trading. M
>> so people would say Paul Suda Jones,
Lewis Bacon, Stan Ducker Miller.
>> Yeah, they also made a lot of money out
of asset management fees.
>> Um that's where they made a huge amount
of money after they got big. But yes,
some of those guys, Lewis,
[clears throat]
Paul, and Stan are all
like five standard deviations talent.
They just don't exist.
Most people don't make money. Why is it
that every brokerage firm, their most
profitable
customers, the people who make the most
P&L are dead ones? Yeah,
>> I mean I've seen more and more of these
crypto traders who are [snorts] not and
there's not many who are not like
loudmouth and who used to make money
trading crypto in 2019 2020 2021 saying
I lost my edge now and the only money I
made I mean I made a lot of money but I
lost it all right the only and I still
made a lot of money but it's just
because I was buying I was holding
Bitcoin
>> and I was doing nothing with it and all
the money I made actually comes from
that. Yes.
>> Yes. And look,
the people who've made the most money
out of crypto are the people who don't
trade it.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, I've used the example of
people like Wes Caceres or even Dan
Moorehead. All of these guys have made a
fortune by doing precisely [\h__\h] all.
>> And yet everybody wants to be the next
trader who scalps it. And it's like I I
don't get it. I just don't get it. And
then it's all about emotion and it's
like angry when it goes down and like
overjoys when it goes up and it's like
it's so it's such a waste of energy.
>> You're saying doing [\h__\h] all Dantiro
would say
[snorts]
you're being patient which is very
different.
>> It is. is actually like you did the
thing, you bought the thing and you're
being it's not that you need to reframe
your mindset which is
>> uh
and I think it's port Jones who said I
want to make money in a trade or
long-term trade by staying as long as
possible right which is the same thing
>> yes and so go back to this universal
code framework output of intelligence
the intelligence is the trade working
out compounding its capital all of that
the units of energy
>> just think of that think of the units of
energy use of buying some Bitcoin and
doing nothing. That is the most
efficient trade you'll ever do in your
life. But what we do is the in
inefficient, which is use vast amounts
of our energy, mental energy, emotional
energy because we want to trade it. So
what you're creating is a system that is
by definition less optimal.
[snorts]
>> Why does more volatility make people
think that crypto is easier to trade?
Well, because they're short-term time
horizon people. So, more volatility for
people who are short-term and there's
people who can make a living from that.
It's just very hard. Even Peter Brandt's
like, "It's a terrible way to make a
living." You know, he's a long-term, you
know, been doing it 40 odd years. It's
not an easy way to make a living. None
of the pit traders from Chicago really
enjoyed it because it's hard to pay your
bills [clears throat] by timing markets
and the emotional, you know, it's not
efficient use of your energy in the end
>> versus in a secular bull market,
just owning the asset, but yes, people
can trade around it and people may want
to do it because it makes them feel good
burning that energy doing that. They
should just
>> it makes them feel productive probably.
>> Yeah. Go and play with AI and just hold
your Bitcoin, you know, do that. Use
your productive energy somewhere else.
>> Yeah.
>> Because it's not the optimal outcome out
outcome.
>> How can people develop patience and
conviction when their portfolio is down
60 to 80%. And stays down down bad for
months like we just had now.
>> Yeah. I don't even care.
That's the thing. I don't care. I live
off my salaries and income
>> and if I've got excess capital and it's
oversold enough, I'm like great, I could
buy some more. Has my thesis changed? Is
tomorrow going to be more digital than
today? Yes, keep buying. If it's two
standard deviations oversold used to be,
great, I can actually make more money in
the future. But people don't see that.
They think the opportunity cost is I've
lost money now. I'm like, no, you can
actually make more money in the future
because you can compound and add money.
people [clears throat] can't see this
and so it doesn't bother me. Um, and you
know, I've gone through all of these in
the past and I know now know what to do,
which is just buy the [\h__\h] dip.
[laughter]
>> You [\h__\h] idiot.
Unless, you know, all suddenly you
believe that crypto is never going to
come back. It's never going to get used.
It's all This is just so improbable. So
they just buy the [\h__\h] debt, you
idiot. [laughter]
And then again, you know, it's free
money.
>> It's free money. It's [cough]
people say it's then people start buying
the dip too early. I get it. It's not
easy. So the discipline is like one or
two standard deviations oversold on the
log trend.
>> Do that. If not, do nothing.
>> Just let the trend play out because it's
noise in the middle. And if it goes
wildly two standard deviations
overbought, you have a massive bull run.
Sure, take some money off, go and buy
yourself something. If not, you don't
need to do anything. You really have to
have traded to really Yeah, you'd have
to trade like three times every five
years. That's with taking money off or
twice every five years just to add to
your bets.
>> Do you think you'll be able to sell sell
some
when you're two standard deviation
above?
>> Yeah.
Yeah, if I need to, if I want to, if I
want to buy something, if I want to take
some lifestyle trips. Yeah,
>> it's hard to do. Right. Right now, for
example, um
the semis, the SMH and the Nvidia,
they're all and Google all gone through
their two standard deviations
>> on their log trend, the long-term one.
So now you have to ask yourself the
really difficult question,
>> which is okay, they can bump up against
it for a long time. We've seen that
before, right? But the question is is
was 2022
a new shift in trend because of what is
happening where so much capital goes
into anything that produces output of
intelligence
>> that we're going to change and
accelerate the trend
>> or you're saying probably
>> probably
>> or
>> or it's a bubble and you should
>> are people always trying to justify
what's happening by saying it's a new
paring shift as usual and you see
discharge like that at some point.
>> It lived through two paradigm shifts.
>> One was the internet.
>> Yeah, it had a big correction,
but it was real. It was an entire
paradigm shift. This one is much bigger.
So, if there's any true paradigm shift,
the largest in humanity is when we're
being replaced by Apex intelligence.
>> There's got to be a probability that
this is going to hyper accelerate.
>> Now, does that make sense? I don't know.
When Anthropic is growing at this speed,
Google's like forward revenues at 22
times. It's nothing for a company
growing at this kind of speed. I mean,
what is going on here is insanity. And
it's not PE ratios going up. It's
[\h__\h] earnings going up. [snorts]
Everybody's making a fortune. And
everyone's like, it's a Ponzi scheme
from one's lending to the other. No,
they're all making money from this
massive Cambrian explosion of
intelligence. And the demand for it, the
demand for intelligence is infinite.
Which is perfect for next question
because
crypto's been boring now for a couple of
months or a year.
AI has been AI has been going crazy.
>> Yeah.
>> We are at a parting shift but we don't
know what's going to affect how it's
going to affect the prices of AI.
[snorts]
>> The charts of AI are like that.
>> Yeah.
But when you see charts like that, you
want to form more.
>> Mhm.
>> Why [snorts] should people stay in
crypto both investing and building when
AI is where it's all happening and we
seem to have this crazy
upon only charts and get rich quick
overnight possibilities like we had in
crypto in 2020 and 2021.
>> People don't have to stay in crypto.
>> Your job is to be a mercenary for your
own capital.
you want to make the most money over
time. For me,
I still think it compounds higher
returns than most of these stocks.
Not than, you know, some of them that
get fully rerated. You know, I've been
in a trade rocket labs, which is, you
know, a New Zealand US company that
sends rockets into space and is one of
the only other private companies
actually sending rockets with government
um contracts. Um I don't know. It's I
don't know how much it's up. It's like
since I bought it. I 13x or something.
Okay. So, there are those opportunities
because we're going through this world
and people should seek those
opportunities. But, you know, can crypto
could sooie do a 13x from here? Easily.
>> Could ETH do a 13x? Yeah, why not? Over
what time period? I don't know. So it's
not it it's always the superior to an
individual equity, but if you want to
buy the NASDAQ or or Bitcoin, when you
look at the ratio between the two, put
the standard deviation bounds on. Where
are we? Two standard deviations
oversold.
>> So [snorts] um Bitcoin and crypto is as
cheap as it has been in its long-term
uptrend versus NASDAQ. Okay, that's it
to me sounds like you should be
allocating more to crypto than you are
to the NASDAQ. But that's not to say
there's not a lot of equity
opportunities as well. That's great.
>> Bitcoin and crypto is as cheap as it has
been in its long-term lock trend.
[clears throat]
>> People have been struggling with crypto
market for a while now. Help us get
optimistic or give us some hope for 2026
2027.
>> Yeah. So
we know that the banks are coming.
Stable coins are big, right? This whole
next 24 months is stable coins. It's
going to drive a huge amounts.
I do have one. I do have a cast card
just so you can get that because I know
they're one of your sponsors. I have
>> um I haven't used it yet, but I don't
like spending my crypto. But um
>> Stable Coins is big.
>> Yeah, Stablecoin's big. It's going to
grow massively.
>> So, we'll see a massive explosion in
that.
>> Um the Clarity Act, it's going to get
signed.
that allows pretty much everybody to
start building on uh blockchain. So that
frees it up. Global liquidity is going
to increase. We still got to roll and
pay for like $8 trillion of interest
payments to come or $6 trillion of
interest payments. So we need to print a
[\h__\h] ton of money to come as well.
Um
crypto has is cheap as it as it has been
against many asset classes. Um and it's
been in a mega trend. I don't see that
stopping. So you've got a cheap entry
point with accelerating use case with
large amounts of money coming to it, you
know, trillions of dollars. I mean,
stable coins are doing like run rate of
like a hundred trillion a year. It's
crazy. And that all is underlying use
case for for chains and it's only going
to increase. And then we've got the
agents. So I'm like, okay. And and
liquidity, they're going to keep
debasing because they have to because
the interest payments are due. The
business cycle is running strong. That
means people are going to have more
earnings and more earnings get recycled
into speculative assets, savings and
other things. So it's like, okay, well
here's the perfect storm. Hunter Horse
has been talking about this. A whole
bunch of people are like, yeah,
>> Christ, if you want to put a perfect
storm of upside here when the market is
so miserable about it because it's gone
down or side well down and then sideways
and is was oversold as it has been by
most metrics. We had the fear and greed
below 10 for I don't know how long. It
was the longest period in history. We
had the lowest reading in the history of
the index. [snorts] And we probably
going to resolve war in the Middle East
permanently, which I think is the
potential outcome here.
Yeah. I mean, what what else do you
want? So that that's the bull case. The
bare case is we don't solve war in the
Middle East.
Um it then drives much larger inflation
than was expected. The tightening cycle
comes, the business cycle gets snubbed
out. Um
and capital starts getting starved if
they have to draw liquidity. That means
there's less financing available for the
tech companies. That means that rate of
intelligence slows down. China would
have to be going through the same issue
because if not, the US would have to
just print money to fund it. So, you
know, there's always a bare case to it.
I don't see it yet.
>> What's the probability for that?
>> I think it's it's probably
70 positive positive 30 negative.
>> You're an amazing investor and you're an
amazing person also.
>> What do you want from me?
>> Nothing. [laughter]
>> I don't trust you.
>> I want you to come back on in another
continent
later this year. Yeah, we didn't said
this just so people This is We've now
done [laughter] London. That was the
first, wasn't it?
>> Singapore the first.
>> Singapore June,
>> Dubai, Dubai, Miami.
>> Yeah.
>> So, we need to figure out where the next
one is.
>> Pretty good.
>> Yeah.
>> I borrowed this question from the Invest
Like the Best podcast.
[snorts]
>> What's the kindest thing that anyone has
ever done for you?
When I listened to Paul Tier Jones
answer that question,
I mentally prepared thought you know
what is that
and now I don't really know
I can't think what the because
everything is made out of kindness you
know kindness is a real attribute that
makes the world go round. It creates
positivity
from people. It creates opportunity just
by being kind and people do it
unexpectedly all the time. And I don't I
can't think of a particular moment in
time because there's so many moments
where people have been kind.
>> To be honest, I thought the same. I was
like,
I don't I don't know how I could answer
this question. Like literally,
>> no. Don't forget he cheated because he
knew
>> he knew in advance he could prepare
everything
>> and he's got to come with a great thing
to show what a great philanthropist he
is.
>> He said we're not going to do it at the
end. We need the beginning. Let's start
with that and they can talk people
remember. So then also you know you know
>> being a speculator is not a very nice
thing to be able to lead with
>> but being a philanthropist and I built
Robin Hood because this kind black man
helped me at a
>> as a kid you know is a is a much softer
way of introducing yourself.
>> Mhm. Thank [snorts] you so much, Raul,
for doing this for a fifth time.
>> This is me showing you kindness.
>> I look I look absolutely I was
>> so boring. I'm I'm bored every time. But
>> I I look forward to the sixth time
already. And I'm sure everyone does,
too. [laughter] He has no choice now. He
needs
>> I don't want to do it. You keep doing
this to me. He's not being kind.
Everybody,
>> thank you so much. That was great.
>> See you next time.
>> It worked. It worked.
>> [\h__\h]
As you probably know by now, I host some
of the biggest name in Bitcoin and
crypto on my podcast, but a lot of the
best stuff never makes it on air. The
Shift newsletter is where I share that
raw behindthe-scene alpha, the insight,
stories, and lessons straight from my
guests that you won't hear anywhere
else. If you want the real inside take
on Bitcoin and crypto, join my
newsletter, The Shift, in the
description down below.